Guide to the Dick Thornburgh Papers, 1932- AIS.1998.30.08
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Dick Thornburgh Papers, Series VIII. Assistant Attorney General, Criminal Division
1975-1977
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Thornburgh, Dick
AIS.1998.30.08
11.25 Linear Feet
Dick Thornburgh was sworn in as Assistant Attorney General on July 8, 1975. The Criminal Division dealt with organized crime and racketeering, fraud, government regulation, narcotics, internal security, management and labor, and general crime. Thornburgh considers his most important contribution the creation of a Public Integrity Section. He was a proponent of the recodification of federal criminal law, a task that remains unfinished today, but for which his interest has continued into his "Ongoing Career" and is evidenced in speeches and op-eds. Thornburgh resigned as Assistant Attorney General effective March 12, 1977, and returned to Pittsburgh where he campaigned for the Pennsylvania governor's office in the 1978 election. The files are arranged in thirteen sections: Speeches; News Releases; Events; Correspondence; Jim Seif's Files; AAG Thornburgh's Files; Memoranda; Articles and Newspaper Clippings; Calendars and Telephone Logs; Court Cases; DOJ Files; Strike Forces; and Issue References. Digital reproductions of portions of the collection are available online.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Dick Thornburgh, February 27, 1998
Previous Citation
Dick Thornburgh Papers, 1932-, AIS.1998.30, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Personal papers; Government; Politics; Pennsylvania -- Politics and government -- 1951-; United States -- Politics and government -- 1974-1977; Political corruption -- United States; Political corruption -- Pennsylvania; Drug traffic; Drug control; Organized crime -- United States; White collar crimes -- United States; Business and Industry; Social action; Environment; Kirkpatrick & Lockhart; Thornburgh, Dick; American Bar Association; United States. Organized Crime Control Act of 1970; United States. Department of Justice. Public Integrity Section; United States. Department of Justice. Criminal Division; United States. Office of the Assistant Attorney General
- Assistant Attorney General, Criminal Division, Department of Justice, 1975-1977; VIII.
  Scope and Contents note
  "I received a March 1975 phone call at home from Attorney General Levi [who] asked if I wished to be considered for the post of Assistant Attorney General in Washington ... While it was hard to give up a post in my home town of Pittsburgh, I simply could not pass up the challenging opportunity to assist in the rehabilitation of the Justice Department in the post-Watergate era" ("Evidence" draft, p. 210). Thornburgh was sworn in as Assistant Attorney General on July 8, 1975, to head the Criminal Division. The Criminal Division was made up of sections that dealt with organized crime and racketeering, fraud, government regulation, narcotics, internal security, management and labor, and general crimes. Jim Seif and Jay Waldman, two men who worked in Thornburgh's U.S. Attorney's Office and continued later to work with Thornburgh during his governorship, joined Thornburgh as special assistants.
  In addition to personnel changes, the structure of the Division was modified as well to reflect new priorities. "To support a stepped-up effort against public corruption, we ... created a Public Integrity Section that could take charge of corruption cases that a U.S. attorney was unable or unwilling to handle. I considered the creation of this section the most important contribution of my tenure at the Criminal Division" (Evidence, p. 64).
  An ongoing project to which Thornburgh attached himself was the recodification of federal criminal law, but the "central task of comprehensive reform remains unfinished today" (Evidence, p. 67). Thornburgh's keen interest in promoting reform continues into his "Ongoing Career," and is evidenced in the online speeches and op-eds.
  "In 1976, Jimmy Carter defeated Gerald Ford in the presidential election, and my tenure at the department drew to a close" (Evidence, p. 71). When Carter was inaugurated Thornburgh was "the most senior remaining member of Attorney General Levi's team to remain in office. Because of a delay in the confirmation of President Carter's choice for attorney general, Griffin Bell, I became the Acting Attorney General at 12 noon on January 20, 1977 and remained in that position for the next five days ... I reverted back to acting deputy attorney general when Judge Bell arrived" ("Evidence" draft, p.254).
  Thornburgh resigned as assistant attorney general effective March 12, 1977, and in an accompanying letter to President Carter's new Attorney General, Griffin Bell, he identified areas of concern for the department as "white collar crime, official corruption, organized crime and trafficking in narcotics and dangerous drugs" ("Evidence" draft p.255), tasks beyond the reach of state and local law enforcement agencies. In closing the letter he states: "There is not, and never has been, anything necessarily inconsistent between a forceful and aggressive law enforcement effort and the absolute observance of the civil rights and civil liberties of all of our citizens ... So, in the final analysis, it is an important part of our professional responsibilities to ensure that such is not the case" ("Evidence" draft, p. 257).
  "Long before I left Washington in March of 1977 to return to Pittsburgh, there had been widespread speculation that I would seek the Pennsylvania governor's office in the following year's election. This had been fueled, in part, by Governor Shapp's charges of 'political' prosecutions against his administration. But the most potent argument for my prospective candidacy derived from public concern about corruption and mismanagement in state government and the widely-acknowledged need to 'clean up Harrisburg'" ("Evidence" draft, p. 259).
  - Speeches, 1.
    Information listed on the folders includes: speech title (if known), group or event to which it was delivered, and location. Relevant additional information can be found in the "Events" Section which follows. The folders contain final copies of the speeches and drafts (when available). The speeches are available here online and can be searched for topics of particular interest.
    - List of Speeches and Testimony Given by Richard L. Thornburgh, Assistant Attorney General, Criminal Division, July 1975 - February 1977 (Box 47, Folder 1)
    - Graduating Class Career Prosecutor Course, National College of District Attorneys, Bates College of Law, University of Texas, Houston, TX, July 25, 1975; 1. (Box 47, Folder 2)
    - "Challenges to Law Enforcement," Wisconsin Chiefs of Police Association, Inc., Rhinelander, WI, August 19, 1975; 2. (Box 47, Folder 3)
    - Graduating Class Advanced International Drug Enforcement School #12, Washington, D.C., August 29, 1975; 3. (Box 47, Folder 4)
    - Excerpts, Pitt Law Alumni Dinner, Pittsburgh, PA, September 26, 1975; 4. (Box 47, Folder 5)
    - Subcommittee on Criminal Justice, Committee on the Judiciary, United States House of Representatives Concerning Bills to Provide for Compensation to Victims of Crime, Washington, D.C., November 18, 1975; 5. (Box 47, Folder 6)
    - "Organized Crime - A Community Concern," Annual Conference of the National Association of Citizens' Crime Commissions, Biloxi, MS, December 1, 1975; 6. (Box 47, Folder 7)
    - "Criminal Collections - A New Slant," Eastern Region Collections Conference for United States Attorneys, Providence, RI, December 2, 1975; 7. (Box 47, Folder 8)
    - Fourth Controlled Substance Unit Conference, New Orleans, LA, December 9, 1975; 8. (Box 47, Folder 9)
    - Tampa Chamber of Commerce, Tampa, FL, December 19, 1975; 9. (Box 47, Folder 10)
    - "The Federal Role in Law Enforcement," Annual Jaycee Week Banquet of the Hanover Jaycees, Hanover, PA, January 22, 1976; 10. (Box 47, Folder 11)
    - "The Justice Department's View of the Bank Protection Act," Seventh National Conference on Bank Security, New Orleans, LA, January 26, 1976; 11. (Box 47, Folder 12)
    - House Committee on Ways and Means on Legislation Concerning Tax Return Confidentiality, Washington, D.C., January 28, 1976; 12. (Box 47, Folder 13)
    - Pittsburgh Jaycees Man of the Year Award, Pittsburgh, PA, February 1, 1976; 13. (Box 47, Folder 14)
    - "White Collar Crime," United States Department of Commerce, California Chamber of Commerce, Los Angeles Chamber of Commerce, Los Angeles, CA, February 3, 1976; 14. (Box 47, Folder 15)
    - Attorneys of the Criminal Division, Washington, D.C., February 12, 1976; 15. (Box 47, Folder 16)
    - "Lawyers and Public Integrity," Philadelphia Bar Association, Philadelphia, PA, March 11, 1976; 16. (Box 47, Folder 17)
    - "Crime and the Business Community," Chamber of Commerce of the Greater Harrisburg Area, New Cumberland, PA, March 26, 1976; 17. (Box 47, Folder 18)
    - "Partners in Crime Prevention and Enforcement, " National Cargo Security Conference, Washington, D.C., March 31, 1976; 18. (Box 47, Folder 19)
    - "Prevention and Enforcement - a Dual Response to the Rise in Crime," National Crime Prevention Association, Chicago, IL, April 8, 1976; 19. (Box 47, Folder 20)
    - "Law Day, 1976 - A Government of Laws, Not of Men," San Antonio Bar Association, San Antonio, TX, April 27, 1976; 20. (Box 47, Folder 21)
    - "Law Day, 1976 - A Government of Laws, Not of Men," Montgomery County Bar Association and Montgomery Chapter of the Federal Bar Association, Maxwell Air Force Base, AL, April 29, 1976; 21. (Box 47, Folder 22)
    - "Law Day, 1976 - A Government of Laws, Not of Men," Allegheny County Bar Association, Pittsburgh, PA, April 30, 1976; 22. (Box 47, Folder 23)
    - "The Effort to Contain Organized Crime - an Overview," Institute on Organized Crime, Philadelphia, PA, May 4, 1976; 23. (Box 47, Folder 24)
    - "Crime and Prevention: A Balance Sheet Approach," Pennsylvania Bankers Association, Atlantic City, New Jersey, May 25, 1976; 24. (Box 47, Folder 25)
    - "A Professional Approach to the Professional Criminal," Conference for a Safe Ohio, Columbus, OH, May 27, 1976; 25. (Box 47, Folder 26)
    - "Fair Trial-Free Press Issues," Judicial Conference of the District of Columbia, Hershey, PA, May 28, 1976; 26. (Box 47, Folder 27)
    - "To the Graduate: a Plea for the Healthy Skeptic," Washington and Jefferson College, Washington, PA, May 29, 1976; 27. (Box 47, Folder 28)
    - "Toward the Assurance of Public Integrity," Cleveland Chapter, Federal Bar Association, Bar Association of Greater Cleveland, Cuyahoga County Bar Association, Cleveland, OH, June 8, 1976; 28. (Box 47, Folder 29)
    - Draft Findings and Recommendations of the Federal Advisory Committee on False Identification, Department of Justice, Washington, D.C., June 14, 1976; 29. (Box 47, Folder 30)
    - Senate Bill 1343 the Right to Financial Privacy Act of 1973, Senate Committee on Banking, Housing and Urban Affairs, Washington, D.C., June 17, 1976; 30. (Box 47, Folder 31)
    - "The Prosecutor's Role in the Search for 'The Truth, the Whole Truth and Nothing but the Truth,' " The Criminal Law Section State Bar of Wisconsin, Fontana, WI, June 18, 1976; 31. (Box 47, Folder 32)
    - "A New Partnership in Crime Prevention," Greater Albuquerque Chamber of Commerce, Albuquerque, NM, July 20, 1976; 32. (Box 47, Folder 33)
    - "The Prosecutor and Drug Abuse," Fifth Controlled Substances Conspiracy Conference, Minneapolis, MN, July 22, 1976; 33. (Box 47, Folder 34)
    - Activities of the Interagency Committee on Auto Theft Prevention, Washington, D.C., August 4, 1976; 34. (Box 47, Folder 35)
    - "New Limitations to Combat Corruption in Government," Better Government Association, Chicago, IL, August 6, 1976; 35. (Box 47, Folder 36)
    - "New Challenges Under the Speedy Trial Act of 1974," Judicial Administration Division American Bar Association, Atlanta, GA, August 7, 1976; 36. (Box 47, Folder 37)
    - "White Collar Crime - An Overview," Federal Bar Association, Washington, D.C., September 16, 1976; 37. (Box 47, Folder 38)
    - "Priorities in Federal Law Enforcement," Pittsburgh Federal Executive Board, Pittsburgh, PA, September 24, 1976; 38. (Box 47, Folder 39)
    - Office of Management and Budget, Washington, D.C., September 28, 1976; 39. (Box 47, Folder 40)
    - "The Challenges of Crime," National Institute of Municipal Law Offices, Las Vegas, NV, October 12, 1976; 40. (Box 47, Folder 41)
    - "Federal Role in Law Enforcement," Annual Federal Law Enforcement Dinner, Western District of Michigan, Grand Rapids, MI, October 21, 1976; 41. (Box 47, Folder 42)
    - "Federal Initiatives Against Public Corruption," Public Contract Law Sections of the American Bar Association, Federal Bar Association and Unified District of Columbia Bar Association, Washington, D.C., November 1, 1976; 42. (Box 47, Folder 43)
    - "The Federal Role in Law Enforcement," Blair County Bar Association, Hollidaysburg, PA, November 5, 1976; 43. (Box 47, Folder 44)
    - "Cargo Security and the Justice Department," American Tracking Association, Inc. Security Council Meeting, Arlington, VA, December 7, 1976; 44. (Box 47, Folder 45)
    - "The War on Organized Crime: New Directions and New Priorities," Federal Law Enforcement Association, New Orleans, LA, December 9, 1976; 45. (Box 47, Folder 46)
    - "Some Thoughts about Criminal Justice ... and the Criminal Division," Rotary Club of Manassas, Manassas, VA, December 15, 1976; 46. (Box 47, Folder 47)
    - "Federal Assistance to State Prosecutors," Prosecutor's Institute of the DE Law School of Widener College, Wilmington, DE, January 11, 1977; 47. (Box 47, Folder 48)
    - "Cooperation in Crime Prevention, Is there any Alternative?" Securities Industry Association Forum on Lost Securities, New York, NY, January 14, 1977; 48. (Box 47, Folder 49)
    - House Subcommittee on Appropriations, Washington, D.C., February 9, 1977; 49. (Box 47, Folder 50)
    - Subcommittee on Criminal Justice, Committee on the Judiciary, United States House of Representatives, Washington, D.C., February 23, 1977; 50. (Box 47, Folder 51)
    - "Program Fraud - a Continuing Challenge," Joint Department of Justice, Department of Housing and Urban Development Training Seminar, Quantico, VA, March 2, 1977; 51. (Box 47, Folder 52)
    - Various Undated Speech Drafts, 1975-1977 (Box 47, Folder 53)
  - News Releases, 2.
    Folders of releases are arranged chronologically. These news releases were issued by the Criminal Division of the Department of Justice and deal with all major topics involving the department, including its criminal investigations. The releases are available here online and may be searched for topics of particular interest.
    - October, 1975-February, 1977 (Box 47, Folder 54)
      - Attorney General, Edward H. Levi, announced new internal procedures authorizing civil suits against any bank, savings and loan, or credit union that violates physical security regulations, October 7, 1975; 1.
      - Federal Grand Jury indictment charged Blue Sea Line with paying illegal rebates to importer, November 7, 1975; 2.
      - Creation of a Public Integrity Section within the Criminal Division of the Department of Justice, January 14, 1976; 3.
      - Appointment of three section chiefs in the Criminal Division of the Department of Justice, March 2, 1976; 4.
      - Japanese prosecutors in the Lockheed investigation met with representatives of the Criminal Division, April 9, 1976; 5.
      - Information in the possession of the Criminal Division relating to Lockheed Corporation was transmitted to the Netherlands Government, April 14, 1976; 6.
      - Documents provided to Italian law enforcement in the Lockheed matter may have been improperly disposed, April 24, 1976; 7.
      - Appointment of William R. Robertson as the head of the U.S. Justice Department's Organized Crime Strike Force in Newark, July 12, 1976; 8.
      - Creation of a new Special Prosecutions Unit within the Attorney General's office, August 20, 1976; 9.
      - Reassignment of two officials in the division: Kurt Muellenberg to head Organized Crime and Racketeering Section and William S. Lynch to become Chief of the Narcotics and Dangerous Drug Section, October 13, 1976; 10.
      - Formation of a task force to investigate allegations of corporate payments to foreign nationals, October 14, 1976; 11.
      - Attorney General announced that U.S. Attorneys will keep their offices open on election day, October 26, 1976; 12.
      - Thornburgh announced that Department of Justice Crime Strike Force offices in St. Louis and New Orleans will be closed within thirty days, October 27, 1976; 13.
      - Thornburgh announced Department of Justice Strike Force in the southern district of New York will merge into the U.S. Attorney's office in that district, November 23, 1976; 14.
      - Criminal use of false identification has become a national problem costing billions of dollars annually, December 7, 1976; 15.
      - Thornburgh announced the Department has petitioned five regulatory agencies for new sets of regulations governing physical security and procedures, December 12, 1976; 16.
      - Federal Grand Jury indicted State Representative Herbert Fineman on criminal charges, January 21, 1977; 17.
      - Federal prosecutions of those involved in public corruption offenses reached a new high, February 10, 1977; 18.
  - Events, 3.
    Folders here are arranged chronologically and the information listed includes event name and location. There is a depth of material available, for example: invitations, correspondence, schedules, background memos, personal notes of Thornburgh's and ephemera. Additionally there may be remarks of a more informal nature which are not included in the online speech files.
    - Commission on Review of National Policy Toward Gambling, Philadelphia, PA, May 29, 1975 (Box 47, Folder 55)
    - Commission on Review of National Policy Toward Gambling, Philadelphia, PA, May 29, 1975 (Box 48, Folder 1)
    - Teacher Training Institute, Fairfax, VA, July 9, 1975 (Box 48, Folder 2)
    - Federal Bar Association, Philadelphia, PA, July 21, 1975 (Box 48, Folder 3)
    - National College of District Attorneys, University of Houston, Career Prosecutor Course Graduation, Houston, TX, July 25, 1975 (Box 48, Folder 4)
    - Wisconsin Chiefs of Police Association, Inc., Rhinelander, WI, August 19, 1975 (Box 48, Folder 5)
    - Advanced International Drug Enforcement School #12 Graduation, Washington, D.C., August 29, 1975 (Box 48, Folder 6)
    - White House Conference on Domestic and Economic Affairs, St. Louis, MO, September 12, 1975 (Box 48, Folder 7-8)
    - PA Tavern Association 22nd Annual Convention, Harrisburg, PA, September 22, 1975 (Box 48, Folder 9)
    - "Marie Torre Show", Pittsburgh, PA, September 23, 1975 (Box 48, Folder 10)
    - First Baptist Church, Pittsburgh, PA, September 23, 1975 (Box 48, Folder 11)
    - Pitt Law Alumni Dinner, Pittsburgh, PA, September 26, 1975 (Box 48, Folder 12)
    - Third Collection Conference for Assistant United States Attorneys, Paraprofessionals and Clerks, Attorney General's Institute, Atlanta, GA, September 30, 1975 (Box 48, Folder 13)
    - National Conference on Organized Crime, Washington, D.C., October 1, 1975 (Box 48, Folder 14)
    - Omnibus Hearing Demonstration Program, Jacksonville, FL, October 2-3, 1975 (Box 48, Folder 15)
    - Conference for Business Executives on Federal Government Operations, Brookings Institute, Washington, D.C., October 7, 1975 (Box 48, Folder 16)
    - Justice Wives Club, Tour of the Justice Building, Washington, D.C., October 20, 1975 (Box 48, Folder 17)
    - 53rd Convention of the Pennsylvania Council of Republican Women, Pittsburgh, PA, October 21,1975 (Box 48, Folder 18)
    - Attorney General's Senior Executives Seminar, Quantico, VA, October 30, 1975 (Box 48, Folder 19)
    - Central Pennsylvania Pitt Club Alumni Association, Harrisburg, PA, November 7, 1975 (Box 48, Folder 20)
    - Wheeling Bureau of Police, Wheeling, WV, November 12, 1975 (Box 48, Folder 21)
    - Scripps-Howard Newspapers Debate on Editorial Policy, Washington, D.C., November 13, 1975 (Box 48, Folder 22)
    - United States Attorneys' Conference, Tucson, AZ, November 19, 1975 (Box 48, Folder 23)
    - Annual Conference of the National Association of Citizens Crime Commissions, Biloxi, MS, December 1, 1975 (Box 48, Folder 24)
    - Controlled Substance Conspiracy Conference, New Orleans, LA, December 9, 1975 (Box 48, Folder 25)
    - Attorney General's 26th Annual Awards Ceremony, Washington, D.C., December 11, 1975 (Box 48, Folder 26)
    - Criminal Division, Organized Crime and Racketeering Section Chief's Meeting, Washington, D.C., December 17, 1975 (Box 48, Folder 27)
    - Greater Tampa Chamber of Commerce "Forecast '76 - Finance," Tampa, FL, December 19, 1975 (Box 48, Folder 28)
    - Meeting with Paul Marcus Concerning the Crime of Conspiracy, Washington, D.C., December 29, 1975 (Box 48, Folder 29)
    - Purchasing Management Association of Pittsburgh, Pittsburgh, PA, January 20, 1976 (Box 48, Folder 30)
    - Annual Hanover Area Jaycees Bosses Night Banquet, Hanover, PA, January 22, 1976 (Box 48, Folder 31)
    - National Conference on Bank Security, New Orleans, LA, January 26, 1976 (Box 48, Folder 32)
    - Pittsburgh Jaycees Dinner: Thornburgh Man of the Year, Pittsburgh, PA, February 1, 1976 (Box 48, Folder 33)
    - Los Angeles Chamber of Commerce "Crimes Against Business" Seminar, Los Angeles, CA, February 3, 1976 (Box 48, Folder 34)
    - Drug Enforcement Administration Conference of Domestic and Foreign Directors, Washington, D.C., February 24, 1976 (Box 48, Folder 35)
    - Harrisburg Area Chamber of Commerce Luncheon, Harrisburg, PA, March 5, 1976 (Box 49, Folder 1)
    - Philadelphia Bar Association, Philadelphia, PA, March 11, 1976 (Box 49, Folder 2)
    - Annual Dinner of the Radio and Television Correspondents Association, Washington, D.C., March 25, 1976 (Box 49, Folder 3)
    - Villanova Law School Student Bar Association, Villanova, PA, March 31, 1976 (Box 49, Folder 4)
    - Mercersburg Academy Magazine Interview, Mercersburg, PA, April 7, 1976 (Box 49, Folder 5)
    - National Crime Prevention Association, Chicago, IL, April 8, 1976 (Box 49, Folder 6)
    - Federal Criminal Investigators Association Law Enforcement Seminar, Arlington, VA, April 24, 1976 (Box 49, Folder 7)
    - San Antonio Bar Association Law Day Luncheon, San Antonio, TX, April 27, 1976 (Box 49, Folder 8)
    - Joint Montgomery City and County Bar Association Dinner, Montgomery, AL, April 29, 1976 (Box 49, Folder 9)
    - Allegheny County Bar Association Law Day U.S.A. Luncheon, Pittsburgh, PA, April 30, 1976 (Box 49, Folder 10)
    - Citizens Crime Commission of Philadelphia, Institute on Organized Crime, Philadelphia, PA, May 4, 1976 (Box 49, Folder 11)
    - School of Law, University of Pittsburgh Graduation, Pittsburgh, PA, May 8, 1976 (Box 49, Folder 12)
    - PA Bar Association Annual Meeting, Philadelphia, PA, May 14, 1976 (Box 49, Folder 13)
    - Pittsburgh Chapter Daughters of the American Revolution Bicentennial Luncheon, Pittsburgh, PA, May 15, 1976 (Box 49, Folder 14)
    - Annual Conference of the Pennsylvania Bankers Association, Atlantic City, NJ, May 25, 1976 (Box 49, Folder 15)
    - Conference for a Safe Ohio, Columbus, OH, May 27, 1976 (Box 49, Folder 16)
    - Annual Judicial Conference of the District of Columbia Circuit, Hershey, PA, May 28, 1976 (Box 49, Folder 17)
    - Washington and Jefferson College Commencement, Washington, PA, May 29, 1976 (Box 49, Folder 18)
    - Robert Morris College Commencement, Coraopolis, PA, June 6, 1976 (Box 49, Folder 19)